Guide to the Carrillo de Albornoz and Aldama Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Carrillo de Albornoz and Aldama family papers
1841-1967
GEN MSS 1089
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.96
(5 boxes) + 1 art, 1 cold storage
The collection includes correspondence, business and legal papers, personal papers, printed ephemera, genealogical research materials, photographs, and a scrapbook documenting the lives of the Carrillo de Albornoz and Aldama families including Isaac Carrillo de Albornoz, René Carrillo de Albornoz, Miguel de Aldama, and other family members who lived in Cuba and the United States in the late 19th and 20th centuries.
Carrillo de Albornoz Family
Aldama Family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Susan Amussen, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 7 (cold storage): Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Isaac Carrillo de Albornoz (1844-1901)
Isaac Carrillo de Albornoz was born in Havana, Cuba in 1844. He was imprisoned during the Ten Years' War (1868-1878), and sentenced to death. After his sentence was commuted he immigrated to the United States and became a citizen in 1873. He lived in New York until the end of the Spanish American War when he returned to Cuba and was appointed to the Supreme Court. He resigned in the fall of 1901 due to health reasons and died in New York in November of the same year. He married Dolores de Aldama (daughter of Miguel de Aldama and Hilaria Font) in New York in 1870. Their children included Mario Carrillo de Albornoz, Edgar Carrillo de Albornoz, and René Carrillo de Albornoz.
Miguel de Aldama (1820-1888)
Miguel de Aldama was born in Havana, Cuba in 1820, and was educated in the United States. A wealthy sugar plantation owner in Cuba, he was a leader of the movement for independence from Spain. Aldama immigrated to the United States during the Cuban Ten Years' War and established a sugar refinery on the Brooklyn, New York waterfront. He returned to Cuba in 1885, and died there in 1888. According to his wishes, he was buried in the family vault at Brooklyn's Green-Wood Cemetery. He married Hilaria Font in 1842, and she predeceased him in 1871. They were the parents of six children.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes correspondence, business and legal papers, personal papers, printed ephemera, genealogical research materials, photographs, and a scrapbook documenting the lives of the Carrillo de Albornoz and Aldama families including Isaac Carrillo de Albornoz, Rene Carrillo de Albornoz, Miguel de Aldama, and other family members who lived in Cuba and the United States in the late 19th and 20th centuries.
Arrangement
Arranged by type of material.
Cuban American families -- New York (State) -- New York; Cubans -- United States; Cuba -- History -- Insurrection, 1868-1878; Cuba -- Social life and customs; Photographs; Aldama, Miguel de; Aldama Family; Carrillo de Albornoz, Isaac, 1844-1901; Carrillo de Albornoz, René; Carrillo de Albornoz Family
- Correspondence
  - General, A-Z, 1846-1963, undated (Box 1)
  - Aldama, Domingo Dulce, 1869, undated (Box 1)
  - Aldama family funeral and cemetery arrangements, 1871-1872 (Box 1)
  - Carrillo de Albornoz, Isaac, 1856-1893 (Box 1)
  - Carrillo de Albornoz, Madame Isaac, 1891,1900, undated (Box 1)
  - Carrillo, Lola, circa 1912-1982 (Box 1)
  - Carrillo de Albornoz, Mario, 1894, undated (Box 1)
  - Carrillo de Albornoz, René, 1895, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Carrillo de Albornoz, René, with his father, 1892-1901; 5 (Box 1)
  - Carrillo de Albornoz, René, with his mother, 1894-1901, undated (Box 1)
- Address book of René Carrillo de Albornoz, 1900 (Box 1)
- Diary of René Carrillo de Albornoz, 1898 (Box 1)
- Diary fragment from a voyage by an unidentified traveler, 1882 May (Box 1)
- Carillo de Albornoz and Aldama family business and legal papers, circa1841-1941; 2 (Box 1)
- School notebook with manuscript notes in French, undated (Box 2)
- Manuscript Spanish dictionary of words in context, undated (Box 2)
- Manuscript index of names, undated (Box 2)
- Manuscript verses in an unidentified hand, 1855, undated (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous drawings and greeting cards, 1887, 1956, undated (Box 2)
- Genealogical research notes and documents, 1967, undated (Box 2)
- Printed ephemera, 1870-1967, undated (Box 2)
- Newspaper clippings, 1889-1901 (Box 2)
- Scrapbook of press clippings and other material relating to the death of Miguel de Aldama, 1888 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Aldama, Miguel de, undated (Box 3)
  - Aldama de Carrillo, Dolores, 1875 March (Box 3)
  - Carrillo, Alicia Dolores, 1904 June (Box 3)
  - Carrillo de Albornoz, Edgar, undated (Box 3)
  - Carrillo de Albornoz, Isaac, undated (Box 3)
  - Carrillo de Albornoz, Mario, undated (Box 3)
  - Carrillo de Albornoz, René, undated (Box 3)
  - Dexter, Alice Pinkus, 1914-1917, undated (Box 3)
  - Marshall, Lola, 1950, undated (Box 3)
  - Pinkus, Alice Ball, 1896,1900, undated (Box 3)
  - Pinkus, Laura Ball, 1874, 1912, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, 1895-1948, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - Photographic negatives, unidentified, undated (Box 3)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Cased photographs
    - Aldama y Carrillo de Albornoz, Dolores de, circa 1869 (Box 4)
    - Pinkus, Laura Ball, undated (Box 4)
    - Unidentified, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified photograph on glass, undated (Box 4)
  - Photograph albums, undated; 2 (Box 5)
- Hand-held fan, framed under glass, undated (Box 6 (Art))
- Restricted Fragile
  Box 7 (cold storage): Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 3, photographic negatives (Box 7 (Cold storage))